Guide to the Alexander Stewart Webb Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alexander Stewart Webb papers
1818-1930
MS 684
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.5
(10 boxes, 2 folios)
Correspondence and papers of Alexander Stewart Webb which detail his personal, military, and academic activities. Webb's military service at Fort Pickens, Florida; as a member of the Army of the Potomac, and with General George Meade during the Civil War is documented, as is his tenure as president of the College of the City of New York.
Webb, Alexander S. (Alexander Stewart), 1835-1911
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of members of the Webb family including Mrs. Eliza Osgood Webb, Anna R. Alexandre, and Mrs. Frederic Schenck, 1936-1964.
Scope and Contents
The Alexander Stewart Webb Collection consists of five boxes of correspondence and four boxes of printed and written material dealing with the public and private life of Alexander Stewart Webb (1835-1911). The span of the collection 1818 to 1930. The early letters are of his mother and other relatives and the later letters concerning him are Written friends to Webb's son and daughters. The bulk of the collection is the letters of Webb during the Civil War and later as President of the College of the City of New York.
The wartime letters of Alexander Stewart Webb to his father, wife, and sister cover Webb's activities, impressions, and thoughts as an officer at Port Pickens, later in the Amy of the Potomac, and ultimately to serving under General Meade in the final decisive battles of the war. Webb was very active the Peninsula campaign, about which he later wrote a book. He played an outstanding role in the battles at Chancellors ville and Gettysburg, in the letter of rich displayed "distinguished personal gallantry" for which he was awarded the Congressional Medal of Honor.
Having been seriously wounded at Spotsylvania, Webb was reassigned to teaching at West Point. He resigned, to accept the presidency of the College of the City of New York in 1869 when assigned to field duty in the West. He was an active administrator in this post and was highly regarded by both students and faculty; his tenure saw a great rise in the prestige and reputation of City College.
During the 1870's, 1880's and 1890's, much of the correspondence deals with the attempt to have Webb's name placed on the U.S. Army officer's reserve list. The bill for this purpose passed either the House or Senate at various times, but it was never passed by both and enacted. Another main topic of the correspondence is the disagreement between two factions over General Meade's conduct at the Battle of Gettysburg. General Webb was one of the leading spokesmen of the pro-Meade group opposing the anti-Meade group led primarily by Generals Butterfield and Doubleday. The conflict reached its height in 1890 at the occasion of the visit of the Count of Paris to the United States.
Webb served as head of City College until his retirement in 1902. He remained active in the civic duties in New York until his death in 1911.
The collection consists of 9 manuscript boxes, one folio, and one folio case containing approximately 4,500 items, donated by various members of the Webb family, including Mrs. Eliza Osgood Webb, Miss Anna R. Alexandre, and Mrs. J. Frederic Schenck, 1936-1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research; due to the nature of the material, box 12 requires staff supervision.
Biographical / Historical
Alexander S. Webb: joined U.S. Army in 1855; served in Minnesota and Florida, and in 1857 became professor of mathematics at West Point; served in Civil War, attaining rank of major-general, and retiring in 1866; returned to teaching at West Point; left the army in 1870; in 1869 became president of College of the City of New York.
Fort Pickens (Fla.); Education; Universities and colleges -- United States; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Educators; Soldiers; Allen, Ethan, 1832-1911; Banes, Charles Henry, 1831-1897; Barnard, Frederick A. P. (Frederick Augustus Porter), 1809-1889; Chamberlain, Joshua Lawrence, 1828-1914; Conkling, Roscoe, 1829-1888; Evarts, William Maxwell, 1818-1901; Fish, Hamilton, II, 1849-1936; Foster, David Johnson, 1857-1912; Jay, John, 1817-1894; Lee, George Washington Custis, 1832-1913; Lincoln, Robert Todd, 1843-1926; Low, Seth, 1850-1916; Lydecker, Charles Edward, 1851-; Meade, George Gordon, 1815-1872; Moore, John, 1826-1907; Morton, Levi P. (Levi Parsons), 1824-1920; Paris, Louis-Philippe-Albert d'Orléans, comte de, 1838-1894; Peck, Theodore Safford, 1843-1918; Porter, Fitz-John, 1822-1901; Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937; Ruggles, George David, 1833-1904; Schaff, Morris, 1840-1929; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891; Sprague, William, 1830-1915; Stanton, Edwin M. (Edwin McMasters), 1814-1869; Tarbell, Ida M. (Ida Minerva), 1857-1944; Van Amringe, J. Howard (John Howard), 1835-1915; Walker, Francis Amasa, 1840-1897; Webb, Alexander S. (Alexander Stewart), 1835-1911; Webb, William Seward, 1851-1926; Wheeler, Joseph, 1836-1906; City University of New York; United States Army. Army of the Potomac
- Inventory, 1818-1930; 4.5 linear feet (9 boxes, 1 folio, 1 folio case)
  - Correspondence, 1818-1863 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1864-1868 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1869-1885 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1886-1896 March (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1896 April-1930, undated (Box 5)
  - Civil War material
    - Books of military dispatches, 1865 February 5-April 16 (Box 6)
    - Journals, 1861 May 4-August 4, undated (Box 6)
    - Record of supply shipments, undated (Box 6)
    - Fitz-John Porter
      - Printed matter re court martial, appeal, summary of case, and biographical sketch (Box 6)
      - Typescripts and manuscript re the battle of Malvern Hill and the character of Porter (Box 6)
    - Gettysburg
      - "Battle of Gettysburg and Personal Recollections of that Battle" by Colonel Fred. Fuger: typescript (Box 7)
      - Manuscripts, printed matter, and clippings re Meade at Gettysburg (Box 7)
      - Biographical sketch of Maj. Gen. Henry W. Slocum (1826-1894): typescript (Box 7)
      - Printed matter (Box 7)
      - Reproduction of painting with caption "A view between the opposing lines at a critical point of the battle" (Box 7)
      - Synopsis of testimony re the location of monument of the 72nd Regt. Pa. Volunteers on Gettysburg Battlefield: typescript (Box 7)
    - Printed matter (Box 7)
    - Photographs
      - "Battle Field of Fredericksburg Va" (Box 7)
      - "Genl Webb's Hdqs" (Box 7)
      - "Commissary Head Quarters ... in Stevensburg Va" (Box 7)
    - Sketches
      - "Sketch of 2nd Manassas, August 29th 1862": annotated printed map (Box 7)
      - "Battles Brigade, Ewells Corps": diagram (Box 7)
      - "Why does not the Army of the Potomac Move???": cartoon (Box 7)
    - "A Recollection" [of Chancellorsville] by Wm. C. Reiff: typescript (Box 7)
  - Writings by Alexander S. Webb (Box 8)
  - Writings about Alexander S. Webb (Box 8)
  - Writings about other Webb family members (Box 9)
  - Photographs of Alexander S. Webb (Box 9)
  - Reproductions of drawings by Alexander S. Webb (Box 9)
  - Printed matter on military subjects (Box 9)
  - Storage cases for memorabilia (Eye glass case, etc.) (Box 10)
  - Military maps (Box 11)
    General
    LIST OF MAPS
    - "Reconnoitering of Chesapeake Bay" (printed), 1818 (Box 11)
    - "Manassas Junction" (printed), 1962 (Box 11)
    - "Sketch Exhibiting the Approach to Richmond from Pamunkey River..." (printed, annotated), [1862?] (Box 11)
    - "Campaign Map: Army of the James" (printed), 1864 (Box 11)
    - "Extract of Military Map of N.E. Virginia" (printed, 2 copies), 1865 (Box 11)
    - "Central Virginia Showing Lieut. Genl. U.S. Grant's Campaign" (printed), [1865?] (Box 11)
    - "Antietam" (printed), 1867 (Box 11)
    - "Appomatox Court House" (printed), 1867 (Box 11)
    - "Bermuda Hundred" (printed), 1867 (Box 11)
    - "Chancellorville" (printed), 1867 (Box 11)
    - "Harper's Ferry" (printed), 1867 (Box 11)
    - "High Bridge and Farmville" (printed), 1867 (Box 11)
    - "Jetersville and Sailors Creek" (printed), 1867 (Box 11)
    - "Petersburg and Five Forks" (printed), 1967 (Box 11)
    - "Spottsylvania Court House" (printed, 2 copies, 1 annotated), 1867 (Box 11)
    - "The Wilderness" (printed), 1867 (Box 11)
    - "Gettysburg and Vicinity" (printed, 2 copies, both annotated), 1885 (Box 11)
    - "Topographical Map of the Vicksburg National Military Park" (printed), 1903 (Box 11)
    - "Gettysburg Battle-Field" (printed), Undated (Box 11)
    - "Map of the Battle Field of Gettysburg" (printed), Undated (Box 11)
    - "Cotton Map No. 2: Battle-Field of Five Forks" (printed, 3 copies), Undated (Box 11)
    - "Map of the Environs of Petersburg" (printed), Undated (Box 11)
    - "Map Showing Route of Marches of the Army of Genl. W.T. Sherman ..." (printed), Undated (Box 11)
    - Fragment of map of Yorktown area (printed, annotated), Undated (Box 11)
    - Unidentified area near Malvern Hill (printed, annotated), Undated (Box 11)
    - Unidentified area near Berkely Landing on the James River (printed), Undated (Box 11)
    - Unidentified area (manuscript sketch indicating troop locations), Undated (Box 11)
  - Newspapers (Box 11)
  - Memorabilia of Bvt Maj Gen Alexander S. Webb
    Conditions Governing Access
    Due to the physical nature of the material in box 12, staff supervision is required.
    - 2nd CORPS BADGE (Box 12)
    - 5th and 6th CORPS MEDAL (Box 12)
      made by Tiffany with bars for the battles of: Antietam, Shepardstown, Snickers Gap, Chancellorsville
    - MEDAL OF THE ARMY OF THE POTOMAC (Box 12)
      made by Tiffany with bars for the battles of:
      Bull Run; Mechanicsville; Guines
      Mechanicsville
      Gaines Mills
      Malvern Hill
      Shepardstown
      Chancellorsville
      Bristoe Station
      Mortons Ford
      Spottsylvania
      Hatchers Run
      Yorktown
      Hanover Court House
      Savage Station
      Antietam
      Snickers Gap
      Gettysburg
      Robertsons Farm
      Wilderness
      Petersburg
    - SOUVENIR MEDAL OF THE ARMY OF THE CUMBERLAND (Box 12)
      reverse side lists the battles of: Chickamuga, Wautalchie, Chattanooga, Lookout Mountain, Mission Ridge
    - MEDAL OF HONOR (Box 12)
      "The Congress to Bvt Maj Genl Alexander S Webb—US Army for distinguished personal gallantry in the battle of Gettysburg—July 1-3, 1863"
    - GAR 33d NATIONAL ENCAMPMENT (Box 12)
      Philadelphia, "made of cannon captured by New York, Penna and Mass Regiments at Fort Fisher"
    - GAR MEDAL (Box 12)
    - ORDER OF THE CINCINNATI (Box 12)
      broach engraved: "Alex S Webb, July 4, 1860"
    - SHOULDER BOARD, BELT BUCKLE and TWO BUTTONS (Box 12)
      from the uniforms of Gen Webb
    - SURVIVORS PFZ 72nd PV MEDAL (Box 12)
      reverse engraved: "presented to Genl Alex S Webb by Assoc of the Survivors 72nd Regt PV December 13, 1886"
    - SOUVENIR PIN US (Box 12)
      Grant Monument Committee, April 27, 1897
    - GUEST MEDAL (Box 12)
      commemorating the dedication: of the Gen Alexander Webb Monument, October 12, 1915, Gettysburg, Pa.
    - POLLAK & SON PIPE (Box 12)
      engraving: "Army of the Potomac—April 1st 1861 to Lee' s Surrender—Yorktown Hanover Mechanicsville Chichominy to the James River Wilderness Spottsylvania Pettersburg Antietam, Gettysburg Chancellorsville Bristoe"
    - IN THE CENTER (Box 12)
      replica of the bronze tablet presented to the College of the City of New York by its officers to commemorate Gen Webb's presidency of that institution 1869-1902
    - ACROSS THIS BOTTOM (Box 12)
      a piece of the original ribbon given by Lafayette to the Society of the Cincinnati when it was first formed shortly after the American Revolutionary War. This ribbon was given to Gen Webb.